A Guide to the Cynthia D. Kinser Papers, 1997-2014
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Cynthia D. Kinser Papers, 1997-2014
The Library of Virginia
51470
65.6 cubic feet (70 boxes).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Case Files are closed until 2045.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Cynthia D. Kinser, Pennington Gap.
Biographical Information
Cynthia Dinah (Fannon) Kinser was born in Pennington Gap, Lee County, Virginia on 20 December 1951. She attended the Unversity of Tennessee (B.A., 1974) and the University of Virginia (J.D., 1977). She served as a magistrate judge for the United States District Court for the Western District of Virginia. She also engaged in private law practice and served as Commonwealth's Attorney for Lee County. Kinser was a bankruptcy trustee and clerked for Judge Glen M. Williams. On 2 May 1997, Kinser was appointed to the Supreme Court of Virginia by Governor George F. Allen to fill the vacancy created by the retirement of Justice Roscoe B. Stephenson. She began her service on 8 July 1997. On 30 January 1998, she was elected by the Virginia General Assembly to a 12-year term. On 31 August 2010, Justice Kinser was elected chief justice to succeed Chief Justice Leroy Rountree Hassell, Sr. She served as chief justice until her retirement on 31 December 2014.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1997-2014, of Cynthia D. Kinser (b. 1951) of Pennington Gap, Lee County, Virginia, relating to her tenure as justice and chief justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia. The collection includes case files, correspondence, subject files, and speeches. The case files are closed until 2045.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I. Case Files.
Series II. Correspondence.
Series III. Subject Files.
Series IV. Speeches.
Contents List
- Series I. Case Files., Extent: 62 boxes. (Box 1-62)
  The case files include opinions, concurrences, and dissents written by Kinser. Some of the files also include draft concurrences or dissents that were not used. The case files are closed until 2045.
  - Case Files. (Box 1-62)
- Series II. Correspondence., Extent: 4 boxes. (Box 63-66)
  The correspondence contains mostly copies of outgoing letters. Subjects include acknowledgements, congratulations, appointments and elections, retirements, invitations, recommendations, thank yous, permissions for various individuals to be excused from attending mandatory judicial conferences, and letters concerning adding names of retiring judges to recall lists.
  - 1997 - 2011 (May). (Box 63, Folder 1-20)
  - 2011 (June) - 2012. (Box 64, Folder 1-19)
  - 2013 - 2014 (July). (Box 65, Folder 1-19)
  - 2014 (August-December). (Box 66, Folder 1-5)
- Series III. Subject Files., Extent: 4 boxes. (Box 66-69)
  The subject files include information on Kinser's appointment, investiture, and reappointment to the Court, interviews, and legislation and studies relating to the operation and procedures of Virginia's courts, such as appellate rules revisions, court technology, judicial boundary realignment and workload, payee notification, and rules of evidence.
  - Appellate Rules Revisions. (Box 66, Folder 6-8)
  - Appellate Rules Revisions Advisory Committee Report. (Box 66, Folder n/a)
  - Appointment, 1997. (Box 66, Folder 9-11)
  - Appointment - Courts of Justice Committees, 1997. (Box 66, Folder 12)
  - Carrico Outstanding Service Award - Chief Justice Hassell. (Box 67, Folder 1)
  - Chief Justice's Pro Bono Summit. (Box 67, Folder 2)
  - Court Technology - Kilgore/Kennedy. (Box 67, Folder 3)
  - Courts of Justice Committees. (Box 67, Folder 4)
  - DC-40 Form Processing - Wise County Circuit COurt. (Box 67, Folder 5)
  - Drug Court Information. (Box 67, Folder 6)
  - Election Day, 2012. (Box 67, Folder 7)
  - Election of Chief Justice. (Box 67, Folder 8)
  - 4-H Foundation. (Box 67, Folder 9)
  - Futures Commission. (Box 67, Folder 10)
  - Investiture and Thank You Letters, 1997. (Box 67, Folder 11)
  - Invocation - Judicial Conference for District Court Judges, December 2011. (Box 67, Folder 12)
  - John Marshall Foundation Advisory Council. (Box 67, Folder 13)
  - Judicial Conference of Virginia - Roanoke, 9-11 May 2011. (Box 67, Folder 14)
  - Judicial Inquiry and Review Commission - "Hearing in Open Court". (Box 67, Folder 15)
  - Judicial Realignment Study, 2011. (Box 67, Folder 16-17)
  - Judicial Workload Assessment. (Box 67, Folder 18)
  - Koontz Opinions Project. (Box 67, Folder 19)
  - Magistrate Judges. (Box 67, Folder 20)
  - Payee Notification. (Box 67, Folder 21-22)
  - Portrait. (Box 68, Folder 1)
  - Reappointment, 2010. (Box 68, Folder 203)
  - Review of Virginia's System of Capital Punishment. (Box 68, Folder 4)
  - Richmond Free Press. (Box 68, Folder 5)
  - Rules of Evidence. (Box 68, Folder 6-11)
  - Supreme Court Historical Society. (Box 68, Folder 12)
  - Supreme Court Letter to Chief Justice Hassell. (Box 68, Folder 13)
  - Supreme Court of Virginia Historical Commission. (Box 68, Folder 14)
  - UVA Lawyer Interview. (Box 68, Folder 15)
  - Virginia Bar Association Interview, 2012. (Box 69, Folder 1)
  - Virginia Legal Aid Society. (Box 69, Folder 2)
  - Virginia State Bar - Disciplinary Matters Website. (Box 69, Folder 3)
  - Weighted Caseload Study Committee. (Box 69, Folder 4)
  - Weighted Caseload Study Committee - Fairfax Bar Association. (Box 69, Folder 5)
- Series IV. Speeches., Extent: 2 boxes. (Box 69-70)
  Most of the speeches in the collection are post-2010. They were delivered at ceremonies and meetings of various bar associations, civic groups, and educational institutions. Topics include appellate review and decision-making, indigent criminal defense, court history, and ethics and professionalism. There are also copies of the State of the Judiciary Address. There are two groups of speeches. The first group are arranged chronologically. The second group are undated speeches, and are arranged alphabetically by topic.
  - Wise County Law Day Luncheon, 1 May 1998. (Box 69, Folder 6)
  - Bristol VA Bar Association, 22 February 2000. (Box 69, Folder 7)
  - Keokee High School, 22 January 2001. (Box 69, Folder 8)
  - Legal Aid, November 2002. (Box 69, Folder 9)
  - Bristol Bar Association, 26 May 2009. (Box 69, Folder 10)
  - Appalachian School of Law, 17 August 2009. (Box 69, Folder 11)
  - Christopher Newport University, 30 March 2010. (Box 69, Folder 12)
  - Lee County Historical Society, November 2010. (Box 69, Folder 13)
  - "Attaining Justice Within the Bounds of Appellate REview" - Jefferson Medal in Law, 2011. (Box 69, Folder 14)
  - 2011 Harry L. Carrico Outstanding Career Service Award. (Box 69, Folder 15)
  - 2011 State of the Judiciary. (Box 69, Folder 16)
  - 4-H Congress, Blacksburg, 20 June 2011. (Box 69, Folder 17)
  - Virginia Circuit Court Clerk's Association, 17 September 2011. (Box 69, Folder 18)
  - Mid-Atlantic Association for Court Management, 19 September 2011. (Box 69, Folder 19)
  - Roanoke Bar Association, 11 October 2011. (Box 69, Folder 20)
  - 2012 Harry L. Carrico Outstanding Career Service Award. (Box 69, Folder 21)
  - 2012 State of the Judiciary. (Box 69, Folder 22)
  - Virginia Board of Bar Examiners, 11 January 2012. (Box 69, Folder 23)
  - Mountain Empire Community College, 21 March 2012. (Box 69, Folder 24)
  - Greater Peninsula Women's Bar Association, 4 April 2012. (Box 69, Folder 25)
  - Virginia State Bar 20th Anniversary Conclave, 22-23 April 2012. (Box 69, Folder 26)
  - Pro Bono Summit, 25 April 2012. (Box 69, Folder 27)
  - Indigent Criminal Defense Advanced Skills for the Experienced Practioner, 4 May 2012. (Box 69, Folder 28)
  - Virginia Bar Association Southwest Virginia CLE, 24 September 2012. (Box 69, Folder 29)
  - Montgomery County Courthouse Dedication, 7 November 2012. (Box 69, Folder 30)
  - 2013 State of the Judiciary. (Box 70, Folder 1)
  - Recognition of Gregory E. Lucyk, Chief Staff Attorney, 27 February 2013. (Box 70, Folder 2)
  - Magistrate Training, November 2013. (Box 70, Folder 3)
  - 2014 Harry L. Carrico Outstanding Career Service Award. (Box 70, Folder 4)
  - 2014 Indigent Criminal Defense Seminar. (Box 70, Folder 5)
  - 2014 Magistrate Training. (Box 70, Folder 6)
  - 2014 State of the Judiciary. (Box 70, Folder 7)
  - Pro Bono Summit, 2 April 2014. (Box 70, Folder 8)
  - Southeastern Chapters of the American Board of Trial Advocates Conference, 1-2 May 2014. (Box 70, Folder 9)
  - Virginia State Bar 75th Anniversary, 4 June 2014. (Box 70, Folder 10)
  - Recognition of Virginia LAw Foundation, 10 September 2014. (Box 70, Folder 11)
  - Hassell Portrait Presentation, 28 October 2014. (Box 70, Folder 12)
  - Virginia State Bar Bench-Bar Dinner, 1 November 2014. (Box 70, Folder 13)
  - Admissions Ceremony, n.d. (Box 70, Folder 14)
  - Appellate Advocacy, n.d. (Box 70, Folder 15)
  - Appellate Judicial Decision-Making, n.d. (Box 70, Folder 16)
  - Avoiding Mistakes That Will Sink Your Appeal, n.d. (Box 70, Folder 17)
  - Citizenship, n.d. (Box 70, Folder 18)
  - Comments on Judicial Decision-Making, n.d. (Box 70, Folder 19)
  - Effective Writing Tips, n.d. (Box 70, Folder 20)
  - Hassell Honor Tree Dedication, n.d. (Box 70, Folder 21)
  - History of Court - Delta Kappa Gamma, n.d. (Box 70, Folder 22)
  - History of Court - Lee County Chamber of Commerce, n.d. (Box 70, Folder 23)
  - Incivility in the Legal Profession, n.d. (Box 70, Folder 24)
  - Jury Duty Script, n.d. (Box 70, Folder 25)
  - Legal Aid Award Luncheon, n.d. (Box 70, Folder 26)
  - MECC Graduation, n.d. (Box 70, Folder 27)
  - Making a Different World of the Legal Profession, n.d. (Box 70, Folder 28)
  - Metro Richmond Women's Bar Association, n.d. (Box 70, Folder 29)
  - Mid-Atlantic Association for Court Management, n.d. (Box 70, Folder 30)
  - The Nuts and Bolts of a Successful Appeal to the the Supreme Court of Virginia: Avoiding the Pitfalls, n.d. (Box 70, Folder 31)
  - Petition for Appeal and Oral Argument, n.d. (Box 70, Folder 32)
  - Professionalism - "Listen to the Voices," n.d. (Box 70, Folder 33)
  - Public Confidence and Trust in the Judicial System, n.d. (Box 70, Folder 34)
  - Relationship With Court, n.d. (Box 70, Folder 35)
  - Recent Developments in Virginia Law Regarding Preservation of Error, Contemporaneous Objection Rule, and Assignments of Error, n.d. (Box 70, Folder 36)
  - Review of Worker's Compensation Cases, n.d. (Box 70, Folder 37)
  - Right of Privacy, n.d. (Box 70, Folder 38)
  - Ten Things I Wish Every Lawyer Knew, n.d. (Box 70, Folder 39)
  - Virginia Women Attorneys Association, n.d. (Box 70, Folder 40)
  - Women in the Law: Our History and Our Future, n.d. (Box 70, Folder 41)
  - Worker's Compensation, n.d. (Box 70, Folder 42)